<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>One warning more to the Baptists before their day be wholly spent and the night cover them ... : with a short answer to a book of Matthew Coffin's one of their teachers ... intituled Faith in Gods promises the saints best weapons : with many queries also for them to answer ... / written by one that hath sat under those shadows with them but hath now found the day in which all shadows fly away, Humphery Wolrich.</title>
            <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09452115</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09452115</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43138</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66860)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43138)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1321:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>One warning more to the Baptists before their day be wholly spent and the night cover them ... : with a short answer to a book of Matthew Coffin's one of their teachers ... intituled Faith in Gods promises the saints best weapons : with many queries also for them to answer ... / written by one that hath sat under those shadows with them but hath now found the day in which all shadows fly away, Humphery Wolrich.</title>
                  <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: Pages stained, some print illegible.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptists --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43138:1"/>
            <p>ONE Warning more TO THE BAPTISTS BEFORE Their Day be wholly ſpent and the Night cover them, in which no man can work for God, which the Lord moved me to write, or elſe I ſhould have been ſilent for ever. With a ſhort Anſwer to a Book of <hi>Matthew Caffin's</hi> one of their Teachers, in <hi>Horſham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> Intituled, <hi>Faith in Gods Promiſes the Saints beſt Weapons.</hi> With many Queries alſo for them to Anſwer. Alſo my deſire is, that all that read it would ſend it to them that they may ſee how they are degenerated from their firſt Love, and are now fighting againſt the Light of the Day, that did formerly ſhine more clear in their Hearts, then now it doth, being ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed over with that which muſt periſh and come to an end. Written by one that hath ſat under thoſe ſhadows with them, but hath now found the day, in which all ſhadows fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. HUMPHERY WOLRICH.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God, then was there no ſhadow of death, or covering over the Life.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Wind-Mill</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:43138:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43138:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Where are the wiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LEt them be confounded for ever, and vexed by a fooliſh people; all the diſputers of the world <hi>where are they?</hi> let their mouths be ſtopped for evermore, let Chriſt ſpeak, and his Eternal Spirit, as in the dayes paſt, and him that ſpake in all his Prophets, who is the ſame <hi>yeſterday</hi> and for <hi>ever,</hi> let him ſpeak; and all keep ſilence, even him whoſe words are Spirit and Life, which the fleſhly mind and carnal mind (that can neither hear nor perceive the things that he ſpeaks) be ſilent before the Lord for ever, and all blind guides that are ſetting up the <hi>ſhadow</hi> inſtead of the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and things that <hi>are ſeen</hi> with a <hi>carnal</hi> and <hi>viſible</hi> eye above thoſe things that are <hi>eternal, everlaſting,</hi> and are not <hi>ſeen</hi> but with <hi>another eye,</hi> nor <hi>heard</hi> but onely with the ear that can <hi>hear</hi> what <hi>the Spirit ſaith,</hi> let this be a <hi>warning</hi> and a <hi>charge</hi> from the Lord to you all, that ye <hi>ſtop your mouths</hi> in the duſt <hi>for ever;</hi> let the wife be mad, and the diſputer, and the contradictious blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer's tongue cleave to the roof of his mouth for ever, the eye is open that runs thorow the earth, and the hand is ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out againſt you all, that is everlaſting, and ye are weighed in an even ballance, and found as light as a thing of nought; you and all your wiſdom is comprehended as in a ſpan, and your Mountain will the Lord threſh with the new threſhing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, and lay it waſte for ever.</p>
            <p>There is a way that the Vulturous eye hath not ſeen, and a path that the fierce Lions whelp hath not trodden in, a way of Holineſſe is it for ever, it is the ſame that changeth not for ever, known is it to the righteous, and the redeemed walk in it for ever, and the ranſomed of the Lord from generation to generation; Now are the Dogs angry for want of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens bread, and the Swine that are feeding on the busks would devour the pearl, and are fighting againſt them that have found it, and cannot feed them therewith, now are their mouths fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with lyes and ſlanders, and their tongues ſet on fire of hell, the poyſon of Aſps is in their hearts, the way of Truth they have not known, there is no fear of God before their eyes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43138:3"/>therefore is the Lord God, the Almighty God riſen againſt all fighters, ſwearers &amp; lyars, and he will daſh to pieces their Idols, and all that riſe up againſt him; the Lord hath ſpoken it, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſhall Reign, and Truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the earth; and Chriſt the corner Stone (rejected of the Builders, abhored of the Nations and deſpiſed of men) will he ſet a top of all; he that hath been rejected, ſhall be exalted on high, and break down all Images, and confound all likeneſſes, the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it; he will turn all but his own glory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſhame, and take the Sons of <hi>Nimrod</hi> that hunted mightily before the Lord in their own net, and all the Children of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> in the work of their own hands will he confound, he will exalt the Life and Power, and darken all ſhadows, and break the forms with the brightneſſe of his riſing, and rent the Vail, and deſtroy the Covering that hath covered the Mercy Seat; for I have ſeen the place of Righteouſneſs and Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is there, and <hi>Sathan</hi> is exalted, and the abomination ſitteth as God in his Temple, where he ought not; alſo I have ſeen the place of Juſtice, and Iniquity hath been there, this have I ſeen in the everlaſting day in which all ſhadows fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, which is dawned in the Hearts of his Choſen, in whom he is become a Leader and an Inſtructer in all Righteouſneſſe, as in the dayes of old a Saviour and a Redeemer, as in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations paſt.</p>
            <p>This is the Lord who ſaith, <hi>I am the Lord, and beſides me there is no Saviour,</hi> he is become a hiding place indeed, a ſhelter and a hiding place to the weary, a covering that is not too narrow is his Spirit become; therefore are the children of old <hi>Adam</hi> onely with the Name of Chriſt, covering themſelves with the ſhadow inſtead of the ſubſtance, and cloathing themſelves with their fig-leave forms, having loſt the image of him who is the Subſtance, Life, Virtue and Goodneſſe of all ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, the end and the Finiſher of them all, the firſt and the laſt, who was and is from everlaſting to everlaſting, the Subſtance of all Virtue, Life and Goodneſſe of all to his people, in all ages was he the ſame and changed not, he was &amp; is &amp; is to come to all that know him, the Rock of Ages, and the Chriſt in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe which followed them, he is a Teacher, Leader and Guide to his People for ever, he is a Horn of Salvation for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43138:3"/>he is the beginner and the end of all that is good, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and Finiſher of the Faith of his people in all Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in this Generation is he the ſame, and in his people doth he fulfil the Righteouſneſſe of the Law, as in the Generations paſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4. Mark <hi>(in us)</hi> all ye that are ſpeaking of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by a Chriſt a far off, who ye never ſaw, and of Faith <hi>in his Promiſes,</hi> whom ye never heard, but are yet dead in your ſins; Now do ye rage and fill your mouths with venome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Babylon</hi> is falling and your kingdom departing; Now do you caſt out your flouds of wickedneſſe to drownd the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child, that will rule you all and vex you in his ſore diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, (mark) the Child is born, the Sun is known, that in the dayes of the Prophets was born, and given unto them, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſaw his day and rejoyced, and heard his voice and was glad, this is he and he doth not change, though to blind man he appears not the ſame; and all the Prophets and Righteous men heard his voice, and he wrought all their works in them &amp; for them, and ſaved his people from their ſins, &amp; took away the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowand deſtroyed death, and ranſomed them from the power of the grave, and did ſuch works in them &amp; for them as never man ever did, is not this the very Chriſt? yea this is he, and beſides him there is no Saviour, neither do I look for another; he opens the blind eye, and the deaf ear he cauſeth to hear, he makes the dumb to ſpeak, and the lame to walk, he opens the heart to diſcipline, and commandeth man to depart from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity, he ſaith, and it cometh to paſſe, as ever; the Winds and the Sea doth he rebuke, and ſtill the proud Waves thereof, as in the Generations paſt, this is the Lords doing, and in my eyes very marvellous, this is his Name and his Memorial (the Lord our Righteouſneſſe) throughout all Generations, this is he that ſaith, <hi>I am the Lord and change not,</hi> that is my Name, and beſides me there is no Saviour; let all Diſputers of this World be confounded before him whoſe way is everlaſting, that ſitteth upon the Flouds, and walketh on the Sea as on dry land, and the waters ſink not under him, that turneth the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into light, and the day light into the ſhadow of death; let all the wiſe to do evil and oppoſe him, be made mad for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and let them not find an arm to help them that cannot ſee the Arm of Gods Salvation, but are comparing the Holy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43138:4"/>One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (the Immanuel) to and with themſelves, and likening the inviſible and incorruptible Redeemer of the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and immortal ſoul unto corruptible man, that are ſetting up the letter inſtead of the eternal quickening Spirit that giveth life, that ſees not a difference betwixt the fleſh that profiteth not, and the fleſh that is the life, and if I ſay the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the World, I lie not, between the word that doth waſh, cleanſe and purifie the Hearts of the Saints, and was like a hammer and a fire in <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and in all the Prophets, and is the ſame and changes not in all Generations, which word they heard and believed in it, and therefore ſpake, and the Word that the Apoſtles did feel, taſte, hear and handle, which was in the beginning with God, and was God, and this is the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the World, and beſides him there is not another, but ye being blind cannot perceive him that took Fleſh upon him, and had a Body prepared to do the will of him that ſet him; if thou haſt an ear to hear or an eye to perceive, this is he that deſcended, and the ſame that aſcended far above all Heavens into the boſom of the Father, and ſitteth on the right hand on the Majeſty on high, and is glorified with the ſame Glory that he had with the Father before the world began, this is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, if thou canſt receive it thou art happy.</p>
            <p>But may not I ſay as once was ſaid to the men of <hi>Galilee, Why ſtand ye gazing? Why are you ſeeking the Living among the Dead?</hi> Is not he the Reſurrection? And is there any life in any other? Is not this he that is the eternal and everlaſting day in which ye ought to walk? And out of the Boſom of the Father did he not proceed, and was one with him, who ſaith, <hi>This is my beloved Son, hear Him?</hi> And the Holy Ghoſt did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the likeneſſe of a Dove, yet was not a Dove; ſo ſay I, and my ſayings are faithful and true, Chriſt the Saviour of the World came in the likeneſſe of ſinful fleſh, and took upon him the form of a Servant, yet was he not ſinful fleſh, but the eternal Son of God, which was begotten of the Spirit and is Spirit; there is a Spiritual Body, and there is a natural Body, there is a corruptible and there is an incorruptible Body, but this is a myſtery to the World; in a few words, time would fail me to declare his Generation to the uttermoſt, I may ſay that which I have ſeen of him; Oh the depth and heighth,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43138:4"/>length and breadth of his unſearchable riches and wiſdom, and how in all generations he hath been to his people an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite treaſure, a boundleſſe fountain, and an everlaſting ſtream of goodneſſe, life, vertue, peace, and pure ſatisfaction in all generations, who was before all, the Authour, Creator, and Maker of all, in whom was Life, and he is not changed, but in him is life eternal, peace everlaſting, and ſatisfaction eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and his life runs through all, diſcerns and beholds all, and ſhines in the darkneſſe, and none can flee from him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any darkneſſe nor ſhadow of death where the worker of iniquity can hide himſelf from his dreadful hand, that it ſhould not find him out; though man being in the firſt birth, and born blind, and a tranſgreſſor from his mothers womb, doth not ſee nor comprehend the Light that hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned him, though it ſhine in his heart, and doth convince all, and reprove all of their ungodly deeds, and hard ſpeeches, that they have wickedly ſpoken againſt the Lord; yea, and it will condemn thee <hi>Matthew Caffin,</hi> for all thy ungod like and unchriſtian-like lyes and ſlanders caſt upon the people whom the Lord hath bleſſed, and choſen for his peculiar treaſure, even thee in whom the Father of lyes ruleth, and his works are wrought in thy wicked heart, out of which cometh ſlanders and lyes abundantly, and them thou doſt invent thy ſelf, and calſt them the <hi>Quakers</hi> errors when thou haſt done, whoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and principle thou knoweſt not, but ſpeakeſt evil of that wch thou art a ſtranger unto, &amp; though thou talkeſt of faith, &amp; of being a Chriſtian indeed, which thou ſayſt few do attain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, yet art thou one of the vain diſputers of the world, &amp; like <hi>Cain</hi> art wounding and ſhooting thy arrows againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and like <hi>Iſhmael</hi> art ſcorning the Lords people, ſaying, the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſaith, <hi>turn to the light within;</hi> this was <hi>Pauls</hi> Commiſſion and the <hi>Quakers</hi> work, which in this world they have to do, this was the Prophets work, and <hi>Johns</hi> meſſage, <hi>to turn people from darkneſſe to the light, and from the Power of Satan to God, Act.</hi> 26.18. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>it was</hi> the Light <hi>that ſhone in the heart which muſt give them the knowledge of the glory of God;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaid, the anointing which was in them, that was truth and nolye, taught them all things, and with this <hi>anointing</hi> or <hi>unction</hi> they were to try the falſe Spirits; though thou ſcorneſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43138:5"/>at the <hi>Quakers,</hi> becauſe their meſſage is <hi>to turn people to the light,</hi> and though it be true that the <hi>light within</hi> was ſufficient (and it is the ſame and changeth not) to all the Fathers which died in the faith to ſave them from all ſin, and redeem them out of all tribulation, and in which Light they walked with God, who is the Fountain and Father of Lights, and they were tranſlated from death to life before ever the Scriptures were written, which thou ſayeſt is the rule to walk by, though the Scriptures do not ſay any ſuch thing, but another, that the Sons of God were both ruled and led by the Spirit of God, and though we do ſay and teſtifie theſe things as the faithful and true ſayings of God, and as <hi>John</hi> did bear witneſſe of him ſo do we, <hi>that he is the true light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world,</hi> yet thoſe things as thou haſt wickedly and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly laid them down, as our principles were never ſpoken nor owned by us, neither do we ſlight the Scriptures at all, but own them as they are and ought to be owned, yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>light</hi> the <hi>bright</hi> and the <hi>morning Star,</hi> that is the ſame and changes not, but ſpake in all the Prophets, the eternal arm and power of the Father to Salvation we ſay is not changed, but is able to ſave now without the Scriptures, as before they were written; ſo this is not to make void the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures at all, which do declare what was the Judge of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and Saints rule in all ages, their guide, and what was the wiſdom and power of God to the ſalvation of their ſouls, and as the Prophets and holy men found them to be in themſelves, and as this Spirit did inſpire them and gave them utterance, ſo they ſpake of him as his People do in the ſame ſpirit in this age; now this is onely <hi>to ſet Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Eternal Son of God</hi> above all <hi>viſible things,</hi> and the chief corner ſtone in his place where it ought to be; and therefore the builders of <hi>Babylon</hi> and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of confuſion, which are ſetting him at nought, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee the hidden treaſure which is bread indeed, nor look any further then the things that are earthly, in whom the treaſure and life is hid, and are feeding upon the <hi>husks</hi> and <hi>ſhadows</hi> with the Swine, are now condemning them that have been in thoſe <hi>carnal Ordinances</hi> and <hi>waſhings,</hi> but could never find the <hi>pearl</hi> in them, where it was not to be found, but now having found him that is living which is not among thoſe dead
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43138:5"/>things, but onely to be found in Spirit, we leave thoſe things behind us, and go on to perfection, and look no longer at the things that are ſeen which are temporal, but at thoſe things that are not ſeen, but in that Light which is eternal, which whilſt we look at and believe in, we have ſtrong conſolation and confidence in him that is our hope, and purifies our hearts; as he doth ariſe he doth alſo condemn fin in the heart, and deſtroy the Devils work where it hath been wrought, which is yet ſtanding in thy heart, and in the hearts of all Lyars, and falſe accuſers, who are ſpeaking evil of thoſe things they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, but as a natural bruit beaſts, wherein they defile themſelves as thou haſt done, it doth finiſh ſin in us, and makes an end of tranſgreſſion, and brings in, and us into his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting righteouſneſſe, which is by faith in his bloud; but the blind will be blind ſtill, and cannot ſee any bloud but that which doth not waſh the heart, nor ſprinkle the Conſcience from dead works, nor know any, nor believe in any Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection but that which doth not give the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God; I ſay, if thou canſt receive it, and believe in him who is the Reſurrection, thou mayeſt, but if otherwiſe, thou ſhouldſt dye in thy ſins, and pine away in thy tranſgreſſions, and then Chriſt is not riſen to thy advantage but condemnation, if thou art yet in thy ſins.</p>
            <p>Therefore thou Hypocrite who art hipt from the Light, and climbed above the door of the ſheep, who is the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible and eternal Light, and he onely it is that gives an entrance into the Kingdom that is incorruptible, eternal, and fadeth not away.</p>
            <p>But many have been ſetting up another Saviour then he that ſaves his people from their ſins, and therefore have his Servants been imagining of a kingdom, power and glory that is of this fading world, and therefore inſtead of hearkning <hi>to the light</hi> and <hi>innocent Lamb</hi> which faith, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this world, if it were my Servants would fight;</hi> therefore ſuch who have rejected the word of the Lord (which word is Light) as thou doſt, and ſcorneſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> for walking in it, they have betaken themſelves to carnal weapons, and gone from the Spiritual weapon, which is the Light, and have ſought for a Kingdom that is of this world, and ſo in their imaginations have ſet up both a viſible Saviour and Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:43138:6"/>
            <p>Therefore try thy ſelf whether thou art in that faith which the juſt lives by, and purifie the heart that comes to ſee the pure God, if not, thou art but a reprobate concerning the faith that is a myſtery held in a pure Conſcience, which was once delivered or given to the Saints, neither ſhalt thou ever have the witneſſe in thy ſelf of thy rejoycing, as many that have been in thy dark and blind condition never had, until they were turned to the Light in their Conſciences, but now can through mercy and grace that is powred out upon his off-ſpring teſtifie (to his glory and praiſe everlaſtingly be it given to him alone who doth the work in us and for us) that in the ſame place where it hath been ſaid unto us, <hi>ye are not my people,</hi> there are we called <hi>the Children of the living God;</hi> at this may the Serpent catch that is curſed of the Lord, but own it if thou canſt, it is thy condemnation in that ſtate thou art in, eternally thou ſhalt witneſſe it true, except thou repenteſt.</p>
            <p>A little I ſhall reaſon with thee concerning thy principle, what ſome of thy brethren which thou and they have affirmed in diſpute.</p>
            <p>Firſt, thou ſay eſt <hi>the eternal Spirit is not the Saviour of the world, but the man Chriſt Jeſus that dyed and was a body which the Apoſtles handled outwardly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Did not Chriſt ſay who is that Spiritual Rock who ſaved <hi>Abraham</hi> and the <hi>Fathers</hi> before that body was, <hi>into thy hands Father I commend my Spirit;</hi> and then did he not give up the Ghoſt and dyed? and when the eternal Spirit did aſcend to the Father, was not the body dead without the Spirit, and lay in the Sepulchre until the ſame Spirit and power of the Father raiſed it again? is your confidence in the fleſh or in the Spirit and power that quickned the dead? do ye believe the Scriptures are true, which ſay, <hi>he ever liveth, and is the ſame yeſterday to day and for ever, I in the Father, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in me?</hi> or do ye believe there was no Saviour before he was born in <hi>Bethlehem?</hi> who was it then in whom <hi>Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved? or who did the Prophet ſpeak of when he ſaith <hi>unto us a child is born, unto us a Son is given?</hi> or what doſt thou in thy dark mind imagine the Prophet meaneth, when he ſaith, <hi>his name ſhall be called wonderful Counſellor, the mighty God, the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Father, the Prince of peace? Iſa.</hi> 9.6. and what was the <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> angry with Chriſt for, as thou art with us? was it not becauſe he ſaid <hi>he was the ſon of God, and before Abraham</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:43138:6"/>
            <p>Thou ſayeſt <hi>Chriſt is not come the ſecond time to you, or to any upon the earth.</hi> My anſwer is, Did not the Saints know Chriſt after the fleſh ſome time, and ſaid they deſired to know him ſo no more? what doſt thou imagine his ſecond appearance to be? was it not <hi>without ſin unto ſalvation?</hi> and did not they witneſſe this, that he was <hi>in them, and they in him,</hi> which ſaved their ſouls from ſin? and were they not kept perfect and pure by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing and power which thou wrangleft againſt, ſo that the wicked one touched them not? doſt thou know what <hi>ſalvation</hi> is, or the <hi>image</hi> and <hi>ſtate</hi> is in which man was created, which thou fighteſt againſt, and ſayeſt <hi>none can come into in this life,</hi> if this be not it which the Saints did witneſſe, in whom he was glorified with the ſame glory he had with the Father before the world began? and whether they were not come to it which ſaid, <hi>as ſin hath abounded, ſo grace and truth which came by Jeſus Chriſt did much more abound?</hi> Alſo ye ſay <hi>Chriſt was never crucified but once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My anſwer is, Chriſt was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> but what private interpretation wilt thou give to theſe Scriptures, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. whether ſuch fools as thou and the <hi>Galatians</hi> were who were gone from the Spirit? and doth not <hi>Paul</hi> ſay Jeſus Chriſt was evidently crucified amongſt them? were they not ſuch as turned againſt the Light which had enlightned them who were become a ſpiritual <hi>Sodom?</hi> did not theſe crucifie to themſelves afreſh, and put him to open ſhame, <hi>Heb</hi> 6.6. Though thou ſayeſt the eternal Spirit hath no bloud, I ſay it is becauſe thou never ſawſt it, nor witneſſed the bloud of the everlaſting Covenant to ſprinkle thy Conſcience, therefore doſt thou thus deny it and tread it under thy feet.</p>
            <p>Again ye affirm, that neither <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>Paul, Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> nor <hi>Jacob</hi> were redeemed out of the curſe, neither were they in the Kingdom of God. My anſwer to you is, God is not the God of the dead but of the living, and ſuch as were lively ſtones did ſay they ſate in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.6. And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith an entrance was miniſtred abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly into the kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith he was wrapped up into the third heavens; but thou that art in the Kingdom of darkneſſe wilt tread upon this, as thou ſayeſt thou doſt, upon the <hi>Quakers</hi> principle, for which cauſe thy ſelf ſhall be trodden in the wine-preſſe of Gods wrath.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:43138:7"/>
            <p>Again ye deny that Chriſt is a Spirit; To which I ſay, God is a Spirit, and that which is born of him is Spirit; and I query of thee what Chriſt thou owneſt, whether he that enlightneth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, or another? and what body was that which thou ſayeſt aſcended, and now ſitteth at the right hand on the Majeſty on high? was it he that firſt deſcended, and came out from God, or another? ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, if thou wilt not deny it, or ſay in thy dark mind who art a Teacher, as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> who was a Ruler in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> concerning regeneration, and the way of the Spirit, <hi>how can theſe things be?</hi> when Chriſt told him a man muſt be born again; he was as blind, yet I dare not ſay ſo wicked as thou, for he came to Jeſus by night, he ſaid <hi>can a man that is old enter into his mothers womb and be born again?</hi> if this be not thy ſtate ſend me an anſwer, and tell me if thou be able, who was that ſpoken of, <hi>John</hi> 1.10. <hi>He was in the world and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not, he came to his own and they received him not, but as many as did receive him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived power to become the ſons of God, which were born not of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible but of the incorruptible ſeed, neither were they born of the will of the fleſh,</hi> Mark, nor as thou art, but of God and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſeed which liveth and abideth for ever. Again, I ask thee who was that which deſcended, and what is it? ſeeing the Scripture ſaith <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10. <hi>he that deſcended is the ſame that aſcended up far above all heavens, that he might fill all things,</hi> doſt thou believe that the Jews did not look upon Chriſt, who had eyes, and ſaw him not to be as very a blaſphemer as thou judges the <hi>Quakers? John</hi> 3.13. <hi>no man hath aſcended up to Heaven but he that came down from Heaven;</hi> mark, was not this a ſtrange word to them, and will it not be as ſtrange to thee? had not thy Father taught thee to wreſt the words of truth to thy own deſtruction; even the Son of man which is in Heaven, was not the Saviour of the world without Father, without Mother, without deſcent, having nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beginning of dayes nor end of life? was not this the Son of God, who is King of Righteouſneſſe, and after that King of Peace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.3. and had not the body which the Jews nailed to the Croſſe a beginning, or was it from all eternity? and was that viſible body and form which he took upon him, was that the form and image of the inviſible God? and was that the firſt born in every Creature? and were all things made by that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible body? and was that body before all things? and do all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43138:7"/>things conſiſt by it, or hath Chriſt two Bodies? ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is not divided,</hi> and though there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Members and Branches, yet is there but one Body or Vine.</p>
            <p>Again you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> ſay, <hi>Its Blaſphemy to ſay all that which was ſpoken by Chriſt,</hi> Mat. 2.24. <hi>was fulfilled in that Generation;</hi> might not thou as well and as truly call Chriſt a Blaſphemer, as thy Brethren the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> did, as to charge the Quakers with Blaſphemy for ſpeaking the very ſame thing and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing it to be true which he did ſpeak, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.34. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, this Generation ſhall not paſſe until all theſe things be fulfilled, Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away, but my words ſhall not paſs away;</hi> can thy earthly heart believe this? nay, nay, the world by wiſdom knows not it, no nor the Angels of Heaven, but he to whom the Angels muſt bow knoweth it right well; our God is riſen of a certain Truth, he will do a work in this Generation, a marvelous work and a Wonder, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the God of the deſpiſed Quakers ſhall work; and who ſhall let him? he will triumph over <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> &amp; over <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Amaleck</hi> will he caſt his ſhooe, <hi>Moab</hi> ſhall be his waſh-pot, the humble ſhall hear thereof and be glad, Kings ſhall melt away, Princes ſhall be as a thing of naught, he will exalt his horn, his ſtrength is as the ſtrength of a Unicorn, in the houſe of <hi>David</hi> is his Scepter known, and his dwelling place is become great in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> eternal God, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords is his Name thoughout all Generations, Kings ſhall hear of him and ſubmit themſelves, Princes ſhall be turned aſide by the brightneſſe of his riſing, who is the Reſurrection and the life, who comprehends the Heavens and the Earth with a ſpan, and layes up the Sea as in ſtore houſes, this is our God, the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and true God which you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> are fighting againſt.</p>
            <p>What was <hi>Pauls</hi> &amp; the Saints Weapons, I querie of you Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts? and what was his Armour which he and the Saints put on? was it not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Light, who is called a Helmet of Salvation and the Sword of the Spirit? Is it not the Word of God which is Light, unto which word <hi>Paul</hi> did commit the Saints, and told them it was able to keep them from falling? Or do you imagine the Letter to be the Armour of Righteouſneſſe, which I ſay doth but only declare of them? Is your faith begotten by the Preaching of the dead letter, which the <hi>Jews</hi> thought to have eternal Life in, or by the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43138:8"/>Preaching of the Goſpel which is the eternal Word of God, which was Preached to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and which was and is and is to come, a Preacher of Righteouſneſſe in all Generations, and which the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Was Preached to every Creature under Heaven where the Scripture is not known nor heard of?</hi> but this light which you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> trample on, I ſay all have ſo heard, ſo as to be convinced thereby though not ſaved, becauſe they have not obeyed; but as the Apoſtle ſaith, ſo ſay I, by the ſame Spirit and Faith, Faith comes by hearing, and hearing by this Word of God; the <hi>Jews</hi> had not this Word and Faith, and therefore fought againſt the Life as ye do, but the Light within they could not indure no more then you, but hated it; Therefore ſaid Chriſt, <hi>Ye ſhall die in your ſins, except ye believe that I am he; the Light is the eye, in which</hi> Abraham <hi>ſaw his day, and by which I will guide my people,</hi> ſaith the Lord; What is that eye that muſt be made blind, and that hand that muſt be cut off? Is it not the eye that ſees not the Son, and therefore is not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied? And was not this eye in <hi>Herod,</hi> which is the eye of the Adulterour, and hunteth for the pretious Life? And was not this life in <hi>Eſau</hi> who miſſed the Bleſſing, and in <hi>Nimrod,</hi> and in all the Children of confuſion who are hunting mightily before the Lord without the Spirit, who is the Lord and ſhould lead you by the Fountains of living Water, and feed you with the Living Bread of Heaven, which Living Bread you are ſeeking among the Graves and Tombs, dead forms, &amp; carnal Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which I ſay with <hi>J. Fuce,</hi> makes nothing perfect, but Chriſt the better Hope, who doth thorowly walk and reform, change and tranſlate out of death into Life, out of darkneſſe into Light, out of Satans power and kingdom into Gods Power and Kingdom as the Saints were; and is not this the ſame ſtate that <hi>Adam</hi> was created in, who was the Son of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either Types, Shadows, Vails, Coverings, Death or Grave, Hell or the Bottomleſs Pit were? What is your Water Baptiſm? Is it not a figure which gives not the anſwer of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? What is your Bread, Wine and Ordinances which ye like the <hi>Jews</hi> ſo much cry up, having loſt the Spirit which the true <hi>Jew,</hi> &amp; they that had the one Baptiſm into the one ſpirit, and the new wine in the Fathers Kingdom, and the living Bread which came down from Heaven had.</p>
            <p>MATTHEW CAFFIN, For the Truths ſake and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43138:8"/>an open enemy to it, and hateſt the Light, and canſt not abide that it ſhould be ſo much Preached. I ſhal anſwer to thoſe things charged againſt us in thy book, ſo far as they are our words and not thy own, with wicked inventions caſt upon us by thy venemous tongue. And as for our Principle, it is the Way, the Truth and the Life, and it is clear and innocent in it ſelf, though its image and beauty hath been more mared by ſuch as thou (who like the Jews are crying up the Ordinances of the Lord, which makes the comers thereunto no more perfect then theirs did) then by any Profeſſors beſides in the Nation, and it will clear it ſelf ſhould we be ſilent, and ſpew ſuch as thou art out of its mouth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt thing thou chargeſt the Quakers with is, <hi>That they ſay the eternal Spirit of Light and Power is the Saviour of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is owned and not denyed, but that I or any of the Quakers deny the man Chriſt Jeſus, is not our Principle, but thy own lie caſt upon us, and my words do not agree with thine, but with the Scripture and Chriſts words, <hi>John</hi> 5. where he ſaith, <hi>Ye have neither heard his voice, nor ſeen his ſhape at any time;</hi> Now if thou ſayſt this was not ſpoken of Chriſt but the Father, I ſay it was ſpoken of both, for they are one, if thou couldſt but believe the Scripture, or own the Light, <hi>John</hi> 14. <hi>I am in the Father, and the Father in me, the words that I ſpeak, I ſpeak not of my ſelf, but the Father that dwelleth in me he doth the work, bleſſed is the eye that ſees him, it is ſatisfied,</hi> verſ. 8. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip <hi>ſaid unto him, Lord ſhew us the Father and it ſufficeth</hi> (mark) <hi>Philip</hi> a hearer with the outward ear, but being dull of hearing, and dim ſighted, at the preſent he was unſatisfied, though he had ſeen and heard with the outward ear, verſ. 9. <hi>Jeſus ſaid unto him, have I been ſo long time with you, and yet haſt thou not known me,</hi> Phillip, <hi>he that hath ſeen me hath ſeen the Father alſo;</hi> but thou ſayeſt, the eyes of all in the Synagogue ſaw him, and were faſtned on him, and thou ſuppoſeſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> have no ſhew of Scripture to prove that they which crucified him had any other eyes; here thy malice hath tranſported thee beyond thy own rule, the Scripture ſaith expreſly, <hi>The Vail was over their Hearts, and they had outward eyes and ſaw him, and ſaid, he was the Carpenters Son,</hi> but Chriſt ſaid, <hi>they were blind leaders of the blind</hi> (mark the Light which he bids them believe in whilſt they had it is the eye) <hi>and that they had eyes and ſaw not, ears and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43138:9"/>heard not, and hearts but underſtood not,</hi> Mark 8.18. Ezek. 12.2. Jer. 5.21.</p>
            <p>Therefore what eye did <hi>Paul</hi> open, or what ear was he ſent to unſtop? and what priſoner was that which he was ſent to proclaim liberty unto? and what was that houſe and priſon he was to bring him out of? what did he miniſter, and what did he miniſter to? was he not a Miniſter of Chriſt, after his own eye was opened, and Chriſt revealed which before was vailed in him? did he not miniſter to the Spirit in priſon? (Anſwer if thou canſt) and ſow the ſeed of eternal life, read <hi>John</hi> 8 47. was not this the cauſe they could not hear Chriſt, becauſe they were of the Devil, for ſaith Jeſus, <hi>He that is of God heareth Gods words,</hi> ye therefore hear them not becauſe ye are not of God; then ſaid the Jews, <hi>ſay we not well, thou art a Samaritane and haſt a Devil?</hi> is not this thy mind concerning my words in my Book, becauſe I ſay <hi>the carnal eye and ear did never ſee nor hear the voice of the Son of God,</hi> verſ. 43. <hi>why do ye not underſtand my ſpeech? even becauſe they cannot hear my words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou ſayeſt <hi>George Fox</hi> ſaid the fleſh of Chriſt is a figure, and <hi>Joſeph Fuce</hi> ſaith, the Baptiſts make fleſh their arm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The words of <hi>George Fox</hi> as thou ſayeſt is in his Book, I never read them there, nor ever heard him ſpeak the words; but this I ſay, there is a fleſh that profiteth not, yea and a vail too, which was a figure of him that was to come, as ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. and I witneſſe the words of <hi>Joſeph Fuce</hi> true, who hath been a Teacher amongſt you my ſelf, that all ſuch as thou art make fleſh their arm, who art an enemy to the light, which is the arm and power of God to Salvation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thou ſayeſt <hi>Humphry Smith</hi> in his Book ſaith, Chriſt is come, and this by thee is counted a great errour; I ſay the ſame, and much more, the Kingdom is come and the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe thereof, glory is come and we are come into it, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is rained down from Heaven, Truth is ſpringed up in the earth, Salvation is come, and we ſit in Heaven with Chriſt; yet do not I ſay or deny but there is a further weight of glory, and the increaſe of this kingdom and glory hath no end; neither do I deny but Chriſt is yet to come the ſecond time, the Kingdom and the Righteouſneſſe thereof is yet to come to all ſuch dark ſots as thou art, although the ſeed the light is come into thee already, to thy condemnation.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43138:9"/>
            <p n="4">4. Thou goes on ſlandering <hi>Humphery Smiths</hi> Book, intituled <hi>The everlaſting Rule,</hi> and ſayeſt in the face of men and Devils he affirms, that there is no other rule, way, means or name by which man ſhall ever come to walk with God, but by that which is manifeſt of God in him. My heart is one with <hi>Humphery Smith</hi> in theſe words, and in the face of the Devil, and againſt him and all ſuch men as take his part, I affirm the ſame, that he which was the Light in whom all the Patriarchs and Fathers walked with God (before the Scriptures (which is thou ſayeſt thy rule and guide) was written) is the Saviour of the world, and changes not, his Spirit a perfect guide and inſtructer in all the wayes of Righteouſneſſe, and beſides him I do not look for another, yet the Scriptures I own, which are things too high for thee who art an enemy to him that giveth life.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall come a little to take notice of the form of thy own words, which begins in the 59. page of thy Book, where thou haſt drawn up ſcornfully many words in thy own form, and replyes an anſwer thy ſelf, and ſayeſt, <hi>Turn to the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Quaker;</hi> this thou doſt not ſpeak ſo as to own it for Truth, or the Light and its teaching ſufficient, but as if it were a doctrine contrary to what God, Angels, Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught; therefore I ſhall prove thee exceeding blind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Scriptures, to all who are not filled with envy, as thou art; thou ſayeſt God ſpake by the Prophets, and all ſhould hear the words that were cryed by the words of the former Prophets, and not to the Light within, as ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again thou ſayeſt <hi>Iohn</hi> ſent two of his Diſciples unto Jeſus, ſaying, <hi>Art thou he that ſhall come, or do we look for another;</hi> but thou ſayeſt the true Light turned him to outward means for his ſatisfaction, which outward means neither I nor any of the <hi>Quakers</hi> deny, if the Light within lead thereunto.</p>
            <p>Again thou ſpeaks of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the people and Souldiers that came unto him, ſaying, <hi>Maſter what ſhall we do?</hi> and thou moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſayeſt <hi>turn to the Light within</hi> ſays the <hi>Quaker;</hi> but ſayeſt thou <hi>Iohn</hi> who had another Spirit then the Light within, ſaith, <hi>let him that hath two coats impart to him that hath none;</hi> exact no more then that which is appointed, <hi>do violence to no man, neither accuſe any man falſly, but be content with your wages,</hi> and ſo thou wouldſt make a great difference, and divide between the Light of Chriſt in the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the Light and Spirit that ſpake
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43138:10"/>in all the Prophets, or as if the Light of Chriſt within the Prophets now adayes did teach to deny the words that were ſpoken by the ſame Chriſt and Light in the former Prophets; doth not the Light within, I appeal to the ſimple amongſt the Baptiſts, which convinceth you of ſin in your bed-chambers, whether it doth not teach to do righteouſly, and impart a coat to him that hath none, or if thou haſt bread to feed the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and to do to thy neighbour, yea and unto all men as thou wouldſt have them to do unto thee, and whether the whole Law and the Prophets be not contained in theſe things? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they which were without the Scripture and outward Law, had not the Law which is Light, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith <hi>Prov</hi> 6.23. written in their hearts, by which nature they did the things ſpoken of in the outward Law? and whether this be to deny the Scripture, or contrary to the words of the former Prophets, or the Apoſtles, to turn people to the Light of Chriſt within, which doth fulfill the Scriptures, and is the end of both the Law and the Prophets, anſwer theſe things or confeſſe them true.</p>
            <p>Again thou goeſt on in thy former manner, ſaying, <hi>a certain young man came to Chriſt and ſaid, what ſhall I do that I may have eternal life?</hi> and the Jews came and demanded <hi>what ſhall we do that we might work the works of God?</hi> and then again mocking ſayeſt, <hi>turn to the Light within</hi> ſays the <hi>Quaker;</hi> but ſayeſt thou as if Chriſt were of another mind, then that they ſhould <hi>turn to the Light within, keep the Commandements, and ſell that which thou haſt and give to the poor;</hi> and alſo to the Jews he ſaid, <hi>this is the work of God, that ye believe in him whom the Father hath ſent, that thou ſayeſt waſt Chriſt himſelf that talked with them, but was not in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> My anſwer is, nay, Chriſt was not in them ſo as he was in the Saints, to juſtifie them, but the Devil and darkneſſe was in them, which had blinded the pure eye, which did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them in their Conſciences many times, as thou thy ſelf haſt been convinced, that never man ſpake as he ſpake, neither were the words which he ſpake the words of one that had a Devil, as they ſaid he had.</p>
            <p>And further I ſay, that Chriſts whole Doctrine, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets did proceed from the Light within, for there is a Spirit in man, and the inſpiration of the Almighty giveth him an underſtanding how to ſpeak, and their very end was to turn them to the Light within; and they teſtified God was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43138:10"/>a Spirit, and dwelt in the Light, and they that walked in the Light had fellowſhip with him, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and in which both them and their worſhip was accepted with the Lord, and all the reſt worſhipped they knew not what, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.4.24. and what if Chriſt had ſaid as the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſay in thy own words, <hi>turn to the Commandement within;</hi> I ſay, and the Spirit of Chriſt in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith the ſame, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. <hi>thy Commandement is Light,</hi> and what if he had ſaid <hi>this is the work of God, that ye believe in him who is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and given for a Commander, &amp; for a Covenant of Light,</hi> wouldſt thou not have ſcorned him as thy Brethren the Jews did, and as thou doſt the <hi>Quakers?</hi> did not <hi>David</hi> ſay <hi>I believe in thy word and it hath quickned me?</hi> and did he not ſay <hi>it is a Light to my feet, and a lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn to my paths?</hi> and that it kept him from ſin, and was the way for a young man to have his way cleanſed, if he took heed thereunto; and doth not <hi>Paul</hi> ſay this word in which <hi>David</hi> believed, and is the Author and begetter of the true faith in all that hearken to it, which faith I know thou art a reprobate concerning, though the Title of thy Book is <hi>Faith in the promiſes is the Saints beſt weapon,</hi> yet thy ſelf haſt another weapon; and as for thy hiding place, ſlanders and lyes is thy refuge, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. is not this word nigh in the heart? and did not Chriſt ſay to the unbelievers who rejected the word and Law which is Light, <hi>While ye have the Light walk in the Light that you may be Children?</hi> and hath not this enlightened every one that cometh into the world? and doth not Chriſt ſay <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. <hi>He that follows me ſhall not abide in darkneſſe, but ſhall receive the Light of Life?</hi> but I ſay and the Lord hath ſaid it, the Life is the Light of man, and ſhineth in the darkneſſe, though ſuch blind guides and ſottiſh Children as thou art comprehend it not, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. verſ. 1. to the 10. Thou bidſt thy Brethren take the ſhield of faith, and ſo concludes thy Book. The Lord hath ſaid thy faith is falſe, and let thy Brethren be warned, leaſt they believe as thou doſt; but as thou ſayeſt in ſcorn, I ſay in the integrity of my heart, let the ſimple among thy Brethren or elſewhere <hi>turn to the Light within,</hi> and word which is nigh them in their hearts, and if thy own day of viſitation be not over, do thou hear and fear; but conſider for the time to come, the Jews had thy word, the Letter, and the unbelievers and Apoſtates had thy rule, guide, and leader, but were reprobates concerning this faith which was once given to the Saints, and came by hearing of the eternal word in their hearts; but how canſt thou believe on him thou haſt not heard, but art vexing thy ſelf becauſe the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:43138:11"/>cry <hi>turn to the word within;</hi> Thou likeſt ſuch a word and rule well, and the Children of thy Father ever did, which thou canſt wreſt and turn as thou doſt the Letter, to fight againſt the Life; but that which is a more ſure word and foundation, a tryed ſtone and a perfect rule from generation to generation of them that ſeek the Lord, this thou canſt not endure; but it is my Crown and the Ornament of the Righteouſneſſe in which I rejoyce, and tread upon the Serpents head; and ſhould I never ſpeak more, this I ſay, the eye is open that ſees thee and comprehends thy muddy mind, thou art weighed in an even ballance, the Lord will bruiſe thee with the ſtone thou art lifting at, and the ſword and weapon which thou fighteſt with ſhall be a perpetual pain and terrour in thy own bowels.</p>
            <p>And in the 59. page of thy Book thou goeſt on in a ſcoffng way to oppoſe the Light within, which is to give the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Chriſt Jeſus, and thou brings the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets words, and John Baptiſts words, and Chriſt and the Apoſtles words, and <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> their words, that ſpeaks of Repentance, and concerning the gifts of the holy Ghoſt, and theſe thou brings to oppoſe the Light within. Now to all ſober people this needs no anſwer, but that thou ſhouldſt not exalt thy ſelf among the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, theſe Queries are ſent unto thee.</p>
            <p>Can any repent or have their minds changed, but they muſt have the Light within and be turned to it? can any receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt, but they muſt be turned to the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? Is not the gift received within? <hi>And further thou goes on and ſayeſt, Believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> And then thou ſcoffeſt and ſayeſt, <hi>The Quakers ſay turn to the Light within.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now can any believe, but ſuch who are turned to the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which gives the Light of the knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Chriſt Jeſus? as <hi>Cor.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>And do not they that believe, come to the Witneſs in themſelves and are paſt from death to life? And is not that Witneſs within? What haſt thou Preached all this while that ſets ſuch things upon Record, that Generations to come may ſee thy Ignorance? This ſhews that thou art not as the Churches was in the Primative times, that canſt not endure the annointing within, nor light within; the annointing within muſt needs be light, and how many of the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> Teachers has brought people to the annointing within them, that they need no man to teach them, but as the ſame annointing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43138:11"/>teacheth them? And how many have they brought to the Light within which ſhines in the heart, to give the knowledge of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God in the Face of Chriſt Jeſus?</p>
            <p>And how many have the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> Teachers brought to the New Covenant, the Law written in their hearts and put in their minds, that they need not teach every man his brother, ſaying, <hi>Know the Lord, for they ſhall all know him, from the leaſt to the greateſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How have you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> Apoſtatized from this practice &amp; Doctrine, who now appear as Antichriſt in oppoſition to it, which was in the Apoſtles dayes, who now look upon Chriſt, and ſee him as the Phariſees did, who with the ſame eye that looks ſtedfaſtly upon him, runs upon him and rages at him; and theſe are them that ſtops the pure eye within, that denies the Light as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did; ſo you are like to ſee with no other eyes then the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did, who know him no further then the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did, which fleſh and blood does not reveal him to be the Son of God, and Chriſt is the ſubſtance of all Figures; yet to the world he is a ſign, ſee if thou canſt read that figure, and he is an example, and wilt thou look for another Chriſt then he that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> becauſe <hi>Humphery Smith</hi> ſayes, <hi>He looks for no other,</hi> are you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> angry at this? he that looks for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, I muſt tell you it is that Antichriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Query, <hi>Whether that was not the Light within, that the Phariſees ſtop their ears to, and cloſed their eyes; if it was not, what was it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Are not all eyes ſtopt, and all ears cloſed till they come to the Light within, and all in the ungenerate and impenitent ſtate, till they come to the Light within?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Is not the Light within, the eye that beholds God and Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>And can any ſee God or Chriſt without the Light within? or can they ſee him with a Natural eye, who is a Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>And is it not the Spiritual eye by which Chriſt is beheld, and is not that within? Or is there any fellowſhip or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity amongſt any people that is of God, but they muſt c me to the Light within?</hi> Anſwer theſe-Queries all you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> who oppoſe the Light within, or elſe for ever let your mouths be ſtopt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Could any one ever hear God, Chriſt, Prophets, Apoſtles or Angels, if it was not with the Light within, which gave to underſtand their words?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Or can any come to the knowledge of the Truth or to Repentance, Faith, or the Gifts of God, or come to Worſhip God in the Spirit and Truth, if they do not come to the Light within.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Or can any know Chriſt to be the Son of God and the Saviour, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43138:12"/>know his Reſurrection and his Blood, and him to be the offering who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the Heavens and reſtors all things, and by what he does reſtore, if it be not by the Light of Chriſt within?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>And do not the Baptiſts ſtick in Bread, Water and Wine inſtead of the ſubſtance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Is this a time for you to brawl, and to jangle, and wrangle about outward things? could the prodigal fill his belly with the husks? Did not he leave the husks when he came to the Fathers houſe? Was not this parable ſpoken to the Jews who lived in outward things? And may not this be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to you who live in outward things, warnglers and fighters about them in the field, and comes not to the Fathers Houſe? Did not</hi> Cain <hi>k ll his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the field, and is not the field the World?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friend, in the fourtieth page of thy book, thou charges the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> to be in a very great error, becauſe they ſay, <hi>The Eternal Spirit in man is the Saviour of the World,</hi> and to contradict this, thou puts a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Chriſt and the Comforter in this ſence; I have ſaid there is a difference as in his ſeveral Adminiſtrations, and as he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ts in one to condemnation, and is near in another to juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in this ſence there is a difference, when he Miniſters wrath, and his everlaſting burnings againſt the wicked, and when he Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Peace, Joy, and everlaſting aſſurance to thoſe that love his Light and have followed it in the way of its Righteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſo I ſay there is a difference, when God who is pure Love, pure Peace in himſelf, hath to do and deal with man, who is joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Seed of <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi> which is reprobated; this was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hated by the Lord, and to the froward and perverſe Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>on, God did alwayes ſhew himſelf froward, though God chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es not neither is he froward, though he ſhew himſelf ſo, and ſtands with his Right arm as an Adverſarie to the wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.26. <hi>With the Pure thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf Pure, with the Merciful thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf Merciful, with an upright man thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf upright, but with the froward thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf froward; verſ.</hi> 25. and ſo though there be diverſities of adminiſtrations, yet is there but one Lord, who is the ſame and changeth not.</p>
            <p>Thou ſayeſt alſo, <hi>The eternal Spirit which dwelt in the Man Chriſt Jeſus, which after the Apoſtles received in them, is called another Comforter, and that by Chriſt himſelf,</hi> which would not come unto the Apoſtles, unleſſe as thou ſayeſt, the true Chriſt went away, and ſo thou wouldſt fain prove that the Comforters which afterware dwelt in the Apoſtles, was not the true Chriſt; and for proof her of, thou <gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
